[intriguing music playing]
[Attenborough] Over the course
of my lifetime,
I've visited many extraordinary places.
[gorilla whines, beats chest]
[Attenborough]
I've met many fascinating creatures…
[gorilla beats chest]
…but there are some
with which I have felt
an especially deep connection.
[gorilla exhales]
They possess a strength and vigor…
[gorilla grunts]
…that far surpasses ours.
But when I look at them,
it's not their size and their power
that fills me with awe.
It is the intelligence and awareness
I see in their eyes
when they look back at me.
They fill me
with an overwhelming sense of wonder
and of fear.
[gorilla whinnies, beats chest]
But not a fear of them.
A fear that I, we,
may have missed something.
Something important.
A deeper understanding
of what and who they are…
[music builds dramatically, fades]
…and what that might mean for us.
I remember the first time
I met mountain gorillas.
[thoughtful music playing]
"Monday 9th January, 1978."
"The perfect cones
of the Virunga volcanoes ahead."
"We start the one-and-a-half-hour walk
up the mountain."
"Slowly, the nondescript bush transforms
into the high-altitude rainforest."
"Long-branch trees loaded
with cushions of epiphytes."
"Green, ribbon-leaved ferns
with wispy, pallid
Spanish moss everywhere."
[birds calling]
"We found a group of females and juveniles
in a small clearing,
and, to my astonishment,
they allowed me to approach."
"This would not have been possible
without the pioneering work
of Dian Fossey."
"She lived among the gorillas,
studying the intimate details
of their lives."
Because we did
as we were instructed by Dian,
they accepted us on those same terms.
"I had to pause and exchange
a deep-throated grunt."
"The reassurance noise
meaning, 'I'm here.'"
Mm.
Their sight, their hearing,
their sense of smell
are so similar to ours
that we see the world
in the same way as they do.
[gorilla grunts softly]
And so, if there was a possibility
of escaping the human condition
and living imaginatively
in another creature's world,
it must be with a gorilla.
What I don't say there,
uh… is that
this wasn't, uh, supposed
to be a film of meeting gorillas directly.
Um… the function of the sequence
was the importance
of the thumb and forefinger…
the opposable thumb and forefinger.
We didn't think we were going to be
in touch with them.
We would just sit there
and talk about them.
I turned. They were lying on the ground.
I turned to look back at the camera.
I felt a weight on my feet.
And I looked down there.
There was little Pablo.
I couldn't talk about the evolution
of the thumb and forefinger.
I just sat back and let it happen.
Look at this lovely little creature.
I mean, absolutely engaging.
You want to hug him.
I… I… J… just… just…
just sheer bliss, really.
Many people would think
it was the most important sequence
in that series.
If not, actually, in my filmed life.
There is more meaning
and mutual understanding
in exchanging a glance with a gorilla
than any other animal I know.
I had no idea at the time
what an incredible life Pablo would lead…
or the legacy he would leave behind.
Now I have the chance
to tell Pablo's story
and that of his descendants
who still inhabit
those mountain slopes in the Virungas.
[gentle music playing]
Almost 50 years later,
this gorilla family,
now known as the Pablo group,
are at a crossroads in their story.
The dominant silverback and the leader
of the group is Gicurasi.
[majestic music playing]
He is one of the oldest
and most experienced gorillas
on the mountain.
And the Pablo group has enjoyed a period
of stability under his leadership.
That stability is, in part,
down to his most important ally.
Teta is the dominant female.
She has the respect of the group,
and they follow her lead.
-[music becomes mysterious]
-[gorillas grunting softly]
Teta and Gicurasi
share a unique bond.
With her by his side,
he has maintained power
for five long years.
[music softens]
They are the heart of this gorilla family.
But Gicurasi is now well beyond
his physical peak.
And there are others waiting in line.
-[music stops]
-[gorilla beats chest]
Ubwuzu…
an up-and-coming silverback.
[chilling music playing]
Very big,
very strong,
with ambitions of his own.
Gicurasi is losing his strength…
and Ubwuzu wants to take over as leader.
[animal trilling in distance]
[Ubwuzu hooting]
[chilling music fades]
[gorillas grunting softly]
But for now,
the group are fixated on Teta's baby.
Just as for us,
a newborn is a source of fascination.
But she's only a few months old,
so Teta must keep her out of harm's way,
especially when things get a bit rowdy.
[lively music playing]
Gorillas of all ages like to play.
It's an important part
of forging and maintaining bonds.
[lively music fades]
But Ubwuzu is not interested
in playing games.
[suspenseful music playing]
Right now, he is focused on Gicurasi.
He has outgrown the older male
and is trying to intimidate him.
[Ubwuzu grunts]
But leading a gorilla group
is not just about brute strength…
as I saw for myself
all those years ago in Rwanda.
"The dominant silverback is Beethoven,
probably 30 years old."
"He has an aggressive strut."
He comes in, and this is a huge animal.
You know, I mean… huge compared with you.
I mean, just one thump from his fist
could crack your head open.
[wistful music playing]
However,
Beethoven had another side to him,
and it was revealed to me
through his relationship
with little Pablo.
Not long after I met him,
his mother disappeared,
and he was left to fend for himself.
Without the protection of his mother,
a gorilla of Pablo's age
would have struggled to survive.
But then something remarkable happened.
Beethoven, the giant silverback,
took him under his wing.
[tender music playing]
He tried his best to care for him
as his mother would have done.
And Pablo was always by his side.
He watched.
And he learned.
With Beethoven as a father figure,
Pablo began to thrive.
It was a relationship
that would change Pablo's life forever.
Just like the gorillas I met,
there are many different personalities
within the Pablo group today.
And there is one who reminds me
of Pablo himself.
Not only does he look very similar,
he seems to have
the same boldness and curiosity.
But he has a special fascination
with one gorilla in particular.
Imfura.
[Imfura grunts]
Imfura is at a difficult age.
He's on the cusp of adulthood,
and his back is beginning
to show signs of silver.
But his mind is still young.
Gorillas are highly social creatures
and exist in a network
of different relationships
that help shape who they are
and who they will become.
It's clear that Imfura has
a playful and caring side.
[Imfura grunts]
But his size and strength are new to him.
[tense music playing]
And it hasn't gone unnoticed.
[animal trilling in distance]
[tense music fades]
[somber music playing]
Imfura has been seriously injured
by Ubwuzu.
It seems brutal,
but every silverback has a violent side.
And it's natural for Ubwuzu
to try to eliminate his competition.
[Imfura grunts]
But Imfura is still young.
And he didn't know how to defend himself.
[somber music fades]
[birds tweeting]
The Pablo group are waking up.
[peaceful music playing]
At 12,000 feet,
this is the very top
of their mountain kingdom.
[peaceful music fades]
[gorilla whining]
[expectant music playing]
Ubwuzu is on the move.
Many silverbacks
have ruled these mountains.
Now Ubwuzu is ready to take his turn.
[Ubwuzu grunts]
[caws]
But the rest of the group
have yet to be convinced,
and his frustration is building.
[growls]
The point is not to frighten them.
It's to show them
how frightening he can be.
How capable he would be as their leader.
Gicurasi is watching.
But for some reason, he does not react.
[expectant music fades]
[mysterious music playing]
When you look at any gorilla,
you can't help but imagine
what it is they're thinking or feeling.
What it is that they want,
or what they intend to do.
It's impossible to know for sure.
We can only observe and wonder.
One thing is certain, however.
Despite their size,
gorillas are complex
and sensitive creatures.
Each one is different
with their own unique personality.
And, like us,
they're shaped
by all their life experiences.
The good
and the bad.
[mysterious music fades]
Imfura's wounds are healing…
but he's staying away from the group.
[sorrowful music playing]
At this stage of life,
male gorillas can become very isolated.
And even their own families
become wary of them.
Young males like Imfura
sometimes choose to leave their group
to start their own family.
And sometimes they're left
with no choice but to leave.
[distant gorilla calls, beats chest]
-There are other groups out there.
-[gorilla beats chest]
Imfura can't see them,
but he can hear them.
[gorilla calls, beats chest]
And some are much larger and more powerful
than the Pablo group.
[screeching]
[grunting]
With such big numbers
and so many silverbacks,
outbreaks of violence are more common.
[screeching, grunting]
Getting caught alone
by one of these large groups
would be extremely dangerous for Imfura.
[sorrowful music fades]
[grunting softly]
Ubwuzu is looking for food
with some of the family.
The Pablo group's range is
about three square miles…
and it contains
many different types of plants
that make up most of their diet.
But gorillas are opportunistic.
And Ubwuzu has stumbled across
something different.
Ants.
[tense music playing]
But these are army ants
who have powerful jaws.
[gorilla groans]
And they bite back.
[gorilla snorts]
[music becomes animated]
[chirps]
[grunting]
[animals screeching]
The excitement brings in others.
[grunting]
One of the jobs of a dominant silverback
is to guide the group
to good feeding areas…
and, more importantly,
to bring the group together.
[animated music fades]
Ubwuzu's influence is growing.
[eerie music playing]
Silverbacks communicate in complex ways…
and body language plays a big part.
Where you sit and how you move says a lot.
Ubwuzu is challenging Gicurasi
by moving directly towards him.
As the group's leader,
Gicurasi should see him off.
But he does nothing.
Teta is watching closely.
Confrontations between silverbacks
can escalate quickly.
Ubwuzu attacks.
[screeching]
Silverbacks are more than twice the size
of an adult man.
[snarling]
They are many times stronger.
[screeching]
And fights can end in death.
[grunting]
[barking]
Ubwuzu emerges unscathed.
But there's no sign of Gicurasi.
[somber music playing]
[grunts]
Gicurasi has survived the fight.
But he's been badly beaten.
Dominated by the younger male
in front of the whole group.
As dominant female,
Teta must show the group who she supports.
She leaves with the older male.
And the group follows.
After leading for five years,
Gicurasi has earned their loyalty.
Ubwuzu has been rejected.
[somber music fades]
Not every silverback has
what it takes to lead.
Success or failure
comes down to character.
I only knew Pablo as a three-year-old,
but it was clear that he was
a unique character, even then.
[gentle music playing]
Having been adopted and raised
by a powerful silverback,
by the time he was 18,
he was ready to lead for himself.
He broke away to form his own group,
the Pablo group.
[whinnying]
However, Pablo was
an unconventional leader.
When he was challenged
by a rival silverback
from within his own group,
instead of fighting,
Pablo took the opportunity
to form a powerful alliance with him.
[music becomes animated]
By replacing aggression with cooperation,
between them, they took the group
from strength to strength.
At their peak,
the Pablo group was 65 in number,
the biggest group
of mountain gorillas ever known.
[music softens]
And among them was a young male
who would one day become leader himself.
Gicurasi.
[music fades]
But now, Gicurasi's dominance
is being challenged.
The question is, does he fight back,
or can he learn to cooperate with Ubwuzu?
[thunder rumbling]
Despite winning the fight with Gicurasi,
Ubwuzu is still not being acknowledged
as leader by the rest of the group.
Or Teta.
Without the support
of the dominant female,
Ubwuzu may never win over the group.
[grunts]
[apprehensive music playing]
[grunting]
But Teta's allegiance may be shifting.
By leaving Gicurasi's side
and joining Ubwuzu,
she's signaling her support
for the younger male.
[grumbles]
And Gicurasi steps aside.
[music intensifies]
[music fades]
[gorilla beats chest]
Ubwuzu is now the leader
of the Pablo group,
but this is just the beginning.
[grunting]
Taking over the leadership is one thing.
Staying on top
and keeping everyone safe is another.
[suspenseful music playing]
[music fades]
-[animal chatters]
-[birds tweeting]
[grunting]
There is a new arrival to the group,
an immigrant female
from the other side of the mountain.
[peaceful music playing]
Inyange has left the group
where she was born
and joined the Pablo group
so she may start a family of her own.
It's a difficult move
but one driven by instinct,
and it avoids inbreeding.
She needs to form
her own relationships here,
but she's still a stranger
to the Pablo group
and must tread carefully.
[grunts softly]
[grumbling]
Ubwuzu and Gicurasi are adjusting
to their new relationship.
Now that Ubwuzu is in charge,
he must learn to temper his aggression,
and Gicurasi must learn
to respect his authority.
It's still tense,
but their body language suggests
a level of cooperation may be developing,
which is putting
the rest of the group at ease.
[droning note playing]
[calm music playing]
As they drift in and out of consciousness,
a powerful sense of togetherness
and belonging is expressed
in a chain of tender physical contacts.
The intimate and unmistakable bonds
of a close-knit gorilla family.
-[music fades]
-[grunts softly]
The younger members of the group
will only rest for so long.
[grunting]
Ubi is also stirring.
And he's leaving his mother to explore.
[grumbles softly]
Imfura is recovering
from yet another beating.
He's now lost nearly all
meaningful contact with the group.
It seems that Ubi is
Imfura's only remaining friend.
[grunting]
[tense music playing]
But something is not right.
[gorilla screeching]
Ubi's mother is close by.
She seems to be sending
a message to Imfura.
"Stay away from my baby."
Everyone is turning their back on Imfura.
[grunting]
[beats chest]
[tense music fades]
Inyange, the newly arrived female,
has been observing the group
for a while now.
Especially Teta.
As dominant female,
this could be
a very important relationship for Inyange.
[hopeful music playing]
If Teta allows Inyange
to be close to her family,
it'll send a message
to the rest of the group.
And Teta seems to be welcoming her.
Even trusting Inyange to hold her baby.
Young females do this instinctively.
It prepares them for motherhood.
Inyange's arrival is a positive sign
for both the Pablo group and Ubwuzu.
Gorilla families are always
looking to grow.
There's strength in numbers.
Inyange has arrived
at an especially good time.
Ubwuzu, having taken over as leader,
is keen to have offspring of his own.
[hooting]
With new females arriving…
[howls]
…and, hopefully, new babies on the way,
the group may well grow
and become more powerful
under Ubwuzu's leadership.
[music becomes somber]
[music fades]
Imfura has been excluded
from group life for many months.
He's now moving down the mountain alone.
-[dramatic drumbeat]
-[tense music playing]
A wall marks the limit
of the gorilla's forest.
Imfura has reached
the edge of their world.
[majestic music playing]
He has crossed into the human world.
People have lived here
for thousands of years.
And they, too, depend on the land.
[music fades]
The relationship
between humans and gorillas
has always been a difficult one.
When I was in Rwanda almost 50 years ago,
poaching had pushed the gorilla population
to the very brink of extinction.
There were only around 250 gorillas left
in the Virunga Mountains.
[nostalgic music playing]
There might not be
mountain gorillas at all
had it not been for Dian Fossey.
When poachers began killing the gorillas
she had come to know and love,
she dedicated her life to protecting them…
by whatever means possible.
Even after her death,
her pioneering study of gorillas
continued.
Over the years,
many others were inspired
to protect the gorillas
from within Rwanda and beyond.
And attempts to conserve them
became increasingly successful.
Today, Rwanda's gorilla population
has largely recovered.
But while their population has grown,
the mountains have not.
[nostalgic music fades]
What does this mean for Imfura?
And where does he go from here?
Many gorillas are crowded
into the same space.
It's changing their behavior
and their relationships with each other.
[melancholy music playing]
Imfura is not welcome in the Pablo group.
He's been up the mountain
and all the way down.
He's running out of options.
He may be destined
to be a lone silverback,
the most unpredictable animals
on the mountain.
[melancholy music fades]
Ubwuzu is now securely on top.
The group is stable, and it's growing.
[delicate music playing]
There are two brand-new babies…
one of which is Inyange's.
Ubwuzu's first offspring as leader.
Gorilla newborns are completely dependent
on their mothers,
and gorilla mothers are completely devoted
to their babies.
They are inseparable
for the first few months of life.
Inyange is a first-time mother
and understandably nervous.
[grunting]
[delicate music fades]
Ubwuzu is keeping a close eye on her,
and he's been doing
a good job protecting her.
But, as the dominant silverback,
Ubwuzu can't only watch over Inyange.
There are other females
who want his attention.
These displays are an invitation to mate.
Ubwuzu accepts
and leaves the group unprotected.
[uneasy music playing]
[wind whistling]
[animal chatters]
While Ubwuzu was distracted,
something terrible has happened.
Inyange's baby has been killed.
[music becomes mournful]
The injuries suggest
that a gorilla was responsible.
The other females
in the group surround her.
Only Inyange knows exactly what happened…
and who is responsible.
She may be a recent arrival to the group,
but her loss seems
to have affected everyone.
Inyange has taken herself away.
But at least she's not alone.
Ubwuzu was the baby's father.
But he failed to defend Inyange
and their baby.
[whines]
[mournful music fades]
[birds tweeting]
It has been four days
since Inyange's baby was killed.
Losing an infant in this way
could cause the group
to lose confidence in their leader
and may even fracture the group.
But for now,
they're huddled around Ubwuzu,
and Inyange is right by his side.
[suspenseful music playing]
Something has frightened her.
Imfura has returned.
Her reaction tells Ubwuzu
everything he needs to know.
Imfura killed Inyange's baby.
And he's now a threat to everyone.
[grunting]
Ubwuzu attacks.
[screeching, grunting]
But now, Imfura is much stronger.
Gicurasi joins in.
[music becomes dramatic]
Imfura gets away.
[dramatic music fades]
But he's not gone far.
For the last year,
while he's been excluded from group life,
he has never left it completely.
[somber music playing]
But now, a line has been crossed.
He has killed a member of his own family.
The group is gathered
around their leader, Ubwuzu.
And now, he's leading them on a mission.
[determined music playing]
Imfura is making his way up the mountain,
but he's not alone.
Ubwuzu is close behind
with Teta and Gicurasi by his side.
They're pushing Imfura all the way out.
[music becomes doleful]
Imfura is crossing
into the next valley alone.
Perhaps he was always
going to end up here.
Or perhaps there's only so many beatings
a gorilla can take.
Imfura may now wander
the mountains alone for years.
Or maybe he will find
a family of his own one day.
Only time will tell.
[doleful music fades]
There is at least one member of the group
who will miss Imfura.
Ubi is probably too young to understand
the events that have unfolded here.
But Imfura was his friend.
And now, his friend has gone.
[wistful music playing]
[grumbles]
However, Ubi, just like little Pablo,
is very adaptable.
And he seems intent
on making a new big friend.
Ubwuzu.
[grumbling]
[whinnies]
It's been a testing year for Ubwuzu,
but he's grown into his role as leader.
[music becomes hopeful]
And maybe now a friendship with Ubi
is exactly what he needs in his life.
Gicurasi is no longer in charge here,
but he's filling a new role by supporting
a younger, stronger silverback.
He has a lot of knowledge
and will be a great help to Ubwuzu.
This may well be
the most important role of his life.
Teta has played a critical part
in supporting the leadership transition,
and she and her family are doing well.
Her baby is now almost two years old.
She is growing in strength
and in character.
[hopeful music fades]
Inyange has had a tough time.
She lost her first baby,
and we can only imagine
that this will have
a lasting impact on her.
But she is now an established member
of the Pablo group…
and part of something that is
at the very heart of gorilla life.
Family.
[optimistic music playing]
The Pablo group is not the perfect family.
No family is.
But they have stuck together
through some very difficult times.
And right now things are looking up
for the Pablo group…
as indeed they are
for the species as a whole.
[optimistic music fades]
Today there are over 600 mountain gorillas
across the Virunga Mountains.
Their population has more than doubled
since I was there almost 50 years ago.
[tender music playing]
It's one of the greatest conservation
success stories that I've witnessed.
And perhaps that's down
to the profound connection people feel
towards gorillas.
It's a connection that has stayed
with me my whole life.
And it all began
with one special little gorilla.
Despite a difficult start in life,
Pablo grew into
a strong and charismatic leader.
He remained devoted to his family
until the very end.
[purrs]
This is some of
the last known footage of Pablo.
At 33 years old,
while defending his group
from a rival gorilla,
the great silverback was killed.
I will never forget him…
or the impact he had on me.
The words I use are,
"There's more meaning
in exchanging a glance with a gorilla
than with any other animal I know."
And I stick by that.
I think that's true.
[tender music fades]
[intriguing music playing]